Guide to the Edith Warman Skinner Papers, 1902-1981 CTC.1984.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Edith Warman Skinner Papers
1902-1981
CTC.1984.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
1.0 linear feet (2 boxes)
This collection relates to Edith Warman Skinner's career as a theatre coach and speech teacher for the performing arts at Carnegie Mellon University (formerly Carnegie Institute of Technology). The collection consists of clippings, papers, programs and photos ca. 1929 -ca. 1978.
Skinner, Edith Warman
Biography
Edith Warman Skinner was born on September 22, 1902 in Moncton, New Brunswick, Canada. She was the third of four daughters born to Herbert Havelock Warman and Agnes Lynn (Orr) Warman. After graduating from high school, Edith moved to the United States and began working at the Beechwood School for Girls in Jenkintown, Pennsylvania. In 1923, she graduated from the Leland Powers School for the Spoken Word in Boston. During her time there, she met Margaret Prendergast McLean, disciple of phonetician William Tilly. Consequently, she became a student of Tilly's and his assistant in 1926. She received her bachelor's and master's degrees from Columbia in 1930 and 1931.
Beginning in 1928, Margaret Hewes (Edith's sister) produced professional summer seasons at the Wharf Theatre in Provincetown, Massachusetts where Skinner coached the company. After 1930, she also instructed apprentices in a full-scale training program - one of the first models for actor-training efforts within a professional company in the United States. In 1935 Hewes turned over control of the Wharf theatre to Skinner. During her tenure as producing director the training program expanded and they produced an acclaimed revival of Ah Wilderness!, starring Sinclair Lewis.
In 1937, Skinner joined the faculty of the Carnegie Institute of Technology (now Carnegie Mellon University) in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. While at Carnegie Institute of Technology, her teaching affected a generation of actors and their training, including William Ball and Ellis Raab. During her tenure at Carnegie Institute of Technology, she also continued her professional coaching work at the Pittsburgh Playhouse and later throughout the country as former student actors and directors required her skills.
She served as a speech consultant for William Ball's American Conservatory Theatre in 1965, during its' one season in Pittsburgh, before it relocated to San Francisco. In the late 1960's Skinner was invited by John Houseman to join the faculty of the soon-to-be-established Juilliard School of Drama. She accepted this appointment and for the next few years commuted between Pittsburgh and New York maintaining a full academic schedule at both schools. She also worked as speech consultant for McCarter Theatre, Princeton, and Ellis Raab's Lincoln Center Production of a Streetcar Named Desire during this time.
After retiring from the Carnegie Institute of Technology in 1974, she moved to New York City and continued her work at Julliard. She was also active with the Theatre Company of the Brooklyn Academy of Music. She died on July 25, 1981.
Scope and Content Notes
The Edith Warman Skinner Collection consists of a single series of subject files that are arranged alphabetically. The files contain newspaper clippings, papers, programs, and photos that related to her speech instruction. In some cases preservation photocopies have been created for researcher use. The information on the Carnegie Institute of Technology in folders 14-17 contain newspaper clippings, grant applications, photographs, and programs. Folder 14 contains an example of the types of tests that Skinner distributed to her students, with notes and corrections on the student's performance. Folder 18 contains similar items for Carnegie Institute of Technology's Summer Drama School at Old Economy Village. The "Live with Distinction" manuscript in folder 55 is a summary of an interview with Skinner that a student completed for a journalism class. Folders 62-64 contain newspaper clippings, correspondence, and programs for several oratorical competitions. Newspaper clippings and correspondence relating to the Pittsburgh Playhouse are within folders 68-69. In box two, folders 12-15 contain newspaper clippings, a caricature, photographs, resumes, and itineraries pertaining to Edith Skinner.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These records were a gift to the University of Pittsburgh.
Previous Citation
Edith Warman Skinner Papers, 1902-1981, CTC.1984.01, Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Edith Warman Skinner Papers, 1902-1981, CTC.20, Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Brooklyn Academy of Music.; Carnegie Institute of Technology. Department of Drama.; Carnegie-Mellon University. Department of Drama.; Houseman, John; Lewis, Sinclair, 1885-1951; O'Neill, Eugene, 1888-1953. Ah, wilderness!; Pittsburgh Playhouse.; Skinner, Edith Warman; Williams, Tennessee, 1911-1983; Acting teachers -- United States; Performing arts -- Study and teaching -- United States; Theater; Theater -- United States; Theater programs
- Subject Files, I.
  - Accounting for Love Poster (Box 1)
  - Alexander Technique (Folder 1)
  - American Conservatory Theatre (ACT) (Folder 2)
  - American Educational Theatre Association Convention (Folder 3)
  - Andrews, Dana (Folder 4)
  - Andrews, Edward (Folder 5)
  - ANTA - New York (Folder 6)
  - Associated Producing Artists (APA) Repertory Co. (Folder 7)
  - Auberjonois, Rene (Folder 8)
  - Ball, William (Folder 9)
  - Bates, Heddie (Folder 10)
  - Battles, Margie (Folder 11)
  - Boettcher, Henry (Folder 12)
  - Bucks Co. Playhouse (Folder 13)
  - Carnegie Institute of Technology (Carnegie-Mellon University) - General (Folder 14)
  - CIT -- Clippings (Folder 15)
  - CIT -- Grant Application (Folder 16)
  - CIT -- Photographs (Folder 17)
  - CIT -- Summer Drama School at Old Economy Village, Ambridge (Folder 18)
  - Carnegie Magazine, May, 1938 (Folder 19)
  - Choder, Jill (Folder 20)
  - Clippings -- Misc (Folder 21)
  - Columbia University Teachers College (Folder 22)
  - Conte, Gino A. (Folder 23)
  - Cornish School, Seattle WA (Folder 24)
  - Correspondence -- Misc. (unidentified) (Folder 25)
  - Crise, George Cotton (Folder 26)
  - Dennis, Morgan (Folder 27)
  - Ebert, Joyce (Folder 28)
  - Ellenbogen, Henry (Folder 29)
  - Eythe, William (Folder 30)
  - Finckel, Bob (Folder 31)
  - France, Rachel - Photograph (Folder 32)
  - Grodin, Charles (Folder 33)
  - Gould, Gordon (Folder 34)
  - Guthrie, Tyrone (Folder 35)
  - Hammond, David (Folder 36)
  - Harris, Rosemary (Folder 37)
  - Hayes, Helen (Folder 38)
  - Heflin, Marta (Folder 39)
  - Hewes, Henry (Folder 40)
  - Hewes, Margaret (Folder 41)
  - Hewes, Richard (Folder 42)
  - Hope, Teri (Folder 43)
  - Houseman, John (Folder 44)
  - Jones, Shirley (Folder 45)
  - Julliard Drama School (Folder 46)
  - Katslas, Milton (Folder 47)
  - Kazan, Elia (Folder 48)
  - Kelly, Kevin (Folder 49)
  - Krantz, Judy (Folder 50)
  - Kurtz, Lee (Folder 51)
  - Lawrence, Tony (Folder 52)
  - Lewis, Sinclair (Folder 53)
  - Lewis, Sinclair - Photographs (Folder 54)
  - "Live with Distinction" (MS) (Folder 55)
  - Maekaill, Dorothy
  - Marchand, Nancy (Folder 56)
  - McKenna, Siobhan (Folder 57)
  - Meyer, Carl (Folder 58)
  - Monich, Tim (Folder 59)
  - Norris, Jan (Folder 60)
  - Ogunquit Playhouse (Folder 61)
  - Oratorical Competitions -- Clippings (Folder 62)
  - Oratorical Competitions -- Correspondence (Folder 63)
  - Oratorical Competitions -- Programs (Folder 64)
  - Page, Austin (Bishop of Pgh) (Folder 65)
  - Photographs -- Misc. (unidentified) (Folder 66)
  - Pittsburgh Drama League (Folder 67)
  - Pittsburgh Playhouse -- Clippings (Folder 68)
  - Pittsburgh Playhouse -- Correspondence (Folder 69)
  - Pittsburgh Theological Seminary (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Powers, Peggy -- Photograph (Folder 2)
  - Programs -- Misc (Folder 3)
  - Raab, Ellis (Folder 4)
  - Rabb, Ellis -- Photograph (Folder 5)
  - Ragin, John (Folder 6)
  - Ratner, Iris (Folder 7)
  - Rome, Sydne (Folder 8)
  - Rosenberg, Arthur (Folder 9)
  - Schmidt, Jimmie (Folder 10)
  - Short, Dewey (Folder 11)
  - Skinner, Edith -- Caricature, "th" (artist unidentified) (Folder 12)
  - Skinner, Edith -- Clippings (Folder 13)
  - Skinner, Edith -- Itineraries, Resumes, etc (Folder 14)
  - Skinner, Edith -- Photographs (Folder 15)
  - Skinner, Neil McFee (Folder 16)
  - Smart, F. (Folder 17)
  - Speech -- Misc. Clippings (Folder 18)
  - Speech -- Notes (Folder 19)
  - Taubman, Howard (Folder 20)
  - Terheyden, Jerry (Folder 21)
  - Theatre -- Misc. Clippings (Folder 22)
  - Thomas, Thom (Folder 23)
  - Warman, H.H. (Folder 24)
  - Wertz, Ricki (Folder 25)
  - Wharf Theatre, Provincetown MA
    - Clippings (Folder 26)
    - Contracts (Folder 27)
    - Financial Documents (Folder 28)
    - House Statistics (Folder 29)
    - Jack Johnson MS (Folder 30)
    - Photographs (Folder 31)
    - Production Photographs (Folder 32)
    - Programs, undated (Folder 33)
    - Programs, 1926 (Folder 34)
    - Programs, 1928 (Folder 35)
    - Programs, 1929 (Folder 36)
    - Programs, 1930 (Folder 37)
    - Programs, 1934 (Folder 38)
    - Programs, 1938 (Folder 39)
    - Programs, 1939 (Folder 40)
    - Programs -- School Brochures (Folder 41)
    - Programs -- School Photographs (Folder 42)
  - Who's Who in American Theatre (Folder 43)
  - Wright Teresa (Folder 44)